<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-08T11:59:56+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A personal page with the blog and CV. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">FOSDEM 2025: A PostgreSQL Community Tradition</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2025/fosdem2025/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSDEM 2025: A PostgreSQL Community Tradition"/><published>2025-02-07T06:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-07T06:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2025/fosdem2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2025/fosdem2025/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>FOSDEM has long been a key event for the PostgreSQL community, and 2025 was no exception. Every year, PostgreSQL developers, contributors, and users worldwide gather in Brussels for a week packed with talks, meetings, and discussions. Our community has a strong tradition at FOSDEM, with a dedicated developer room, a booth, and numerous side events</p> <p>One of the most recognizable FOSDEM traditions is <strong>FOSDEM Weather</strong> — a perfect mix of rain, cold, and clouds that always greets us in Brussels. Over the years, we even started selling PostgreSQL-branded umbrellas at our booth, and you could track the weather by watching the sales spike! But this year, for the first time in a while, the weather was <strong>sunny and perfect</strong> — so we joked that the weather was trying to lower our sales. 😄</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/postgres-booth-fosdem-2025-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/postgres-booth-fosdem-2025-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/postgres-booth-fosdem-2025-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/postgres-booth-fosdem-2025.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="a-busy-week-for-postgresql">A Busy Week for PostgreSQL</h2> <p>FOSDEM week is always busy for the PostgreSQL community, with multiple events happening alongside the main conference:</p> <h3 id="p2d2-conference"><strong>P2D2 Conference</strong></h3> <p>Held earlier in the week, the <strong>Prague PostgreSQL Developer Day (P2D2)</strong> is a major PostgreSQL event that gathers experts for in-depth discussions. For a detailed experience of the event, check out <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en/my-first-experience-at-p2d2/">Ants Aasma’s blog post</a>.</p> <h3 id="postgresql-developer-meeting"><strong>PostgreSQL Developer Meeting</strong></h3> <p>On <strong>Thursday, January 30th</strong>, PostgreSQL core developers and contributors held a private developer meeting to discuss ongoing projects, significant challenges, and future PostgreSQL development. More details can be found on the <a href="https://2025.fosdempgday.org/devmeeting/">official event page</a>.</p> <h3 id="fosdem-pgday"><strong>FOSDEM PGDay</strong></h3> <p>On <strong>Friday, January 31st</strong>, we had <strong>FOSDEM PGDay</strong>, a full-day PostgreSQL conference. The schedule featured talks on a wide range of PostgreSQL topics, from performance tuning to backups and new features. The complete schedule is available <a href="https://www.postgresql.eu/events/fosdem2025/schedule/">here</a>.</p> <h3 id="postgresql-devroom-at-fosdem"><strong>PostgreSQL Devroom at FOSDEM</strong></h3> <p>The <strong>PostgreSQL Devroom</strong> took place on <strong>Sunday, February 2nd</strong>, featuring sessions on database performance, replication, analytics, AI/ML, and more. This year, we had great discussions about PostgreSQL internals, best practices, and real-world use cases. You can find the complete session list <a href="https://fosdem.org/2025/schedule/track/postgresql/">here</a>. The talk records will be available shortly.</p> <h2 id="community--networking">Community &amp; Networking</h2> <p>FOSDEM is not just about talks—it’s about meeting people, sharing ideas, and strengthening the community. As usual, there were plenty of social events and informal gatherings.</p> <p>One of the highlights for me was attending the <strong>Google Summer of Code (GSoC) event on Saturday evening</strong>, where I had the chance to meet new and long-time friends. GSoC continues to be an essential program for PostgreSQL, and it was great to see the enthusiasm for mentoring and open-source contributions. Right now, PostgreSQL org is gathering <a href="https://wiki.postgresql.org/wiki/GSoC_2025">project ideas and mentors</a>. If you want to be a mentor, you still have time until February 10th!</p> <h2 id="contributions--recognition">Contributions &amp; Recognition</h2> <p>This year’s central topic of discussion was <strong>contributions</strong>: what counts as a contribution, how we measure it, and how we recognize non-code contributions. Our community relies on the work of many people beyond just developers: event organizers, documentation writers, speakers, translators, and advocates all play a massive role in making PostgreSQL what it is today.</p> <p>To help highlight and recognize these contributions, we put a lot of effort into building our new website: <strong><a href="https://postgres-contrib.org/">postgres-contrib.org</a></strong>. This platform helps track contributions and provides a way to nominate and recognize those who support the community.</p> <h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2> <p>The <strong>spirit of the PostgreSQL community</strong> is what makes FOSDEM so special every year. I want to extend my <strong>huge thanks</strong> to all the volunteers, organizers, and contributors who made this event possible.</p> <p>Special thanks to:</p> <ul> <li>The <a href="https://2025.fosdempgday.org/callforpapers/">Call for Papers team</a> (which I was part of) for reviewing and selecting the talks.</li> <li>All <strong>speakers</strong> who shared their knowledge.</li> <li>The <strong>attendees</strong> who made the devroom lively and interactive.</li> </ul> <p>A special shoutout to <strong>volunteers</strong>, both scheduled and spontaneous. While we had a volunteer schedule for the booth, many community members stepped up to help when needed. For example, <strong>Bruce Momjian</strong> spent hours assisting visitors at the booth, helping find PostgreSQL T-shirts and hoodies in the correct sizes. And <strong>Ants Aasma</strong> helped a team of bouncers (well, pg bouncers, if you know what I mean ;) ). Many others did the same, proving once again that our community is built on <strong>collaboration and generosity</strong>.</p> <p>We had a fantastic time at FOSDEM 2025, and I can’t wait to do it all again next year!</p> <p>Until then, keep contributing and keep the PostgreSQL spirit alive! 🚀</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/pavlo-golub-fosdem-2025-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/pavlo-golub-fosdem-2025-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/pavlo-golub-fosdem-2025-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/pavlo-golub-fosdem-2025.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="community"/><category term="fosdem"/><category term="events"/><category term="postgresql"/><category term="personal"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[FOSDEM has long been a key event for the PostgreSQL community, and 2025 was no exception. Every year, PostgreSQL developers, contributors, and users worldwide gather in Brussels for a week packed with talks, meetings, and discussions. Our community has a strong tradition at FOSDEM, with a dedicated developer room, a booth, and numerous side events]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Join PostgreSQL in Google Summer of Code 2025!</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2025/GSoC-2025/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Join PostgreSQL in Google Summer of Code 2025!"/><published>2025-01-29T06:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-29T06:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2025/GSoC-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2025/GSoC-2025/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="a-legacy-of-postgresql-in-gsoc">A Legacy of PostgreSQL in GSoC</h2> <p>Google Summer of Code 2025 is here, and PostgreSQL is once again proud to participate in this amazing program! Over the years, many talented contributors have started their PostgreSQL journey through GSoC, with some becoming long-term members of our community. Their commitment has helped improve PostgreSQL and its ecosystem, making this program an essential part of our growth and innovation.</p> <p>Looking ahead, we are excited for new ideas, fresh contributors, and more diversity in projects, mentors, and mentees. PostgreSQL welcomes everyone who wants to contribute and learn, and we encourage <strong>both new and experienced community members to get involved</strong>.</p> <h2 id="whats-new-for-gsoc-2025">What’s New for GSoC 2025?</h2> <p>This year, the GSoC team is particularly <strong>looking to support more security and AI/ML projects</strong>. If you know of an <strong>AI/ML or security-focused open-source project</strong>, encourage them to apply for GSoC 2025!</p> <h2 id="who-can-participate">Who Can Participate?</h2> <p>GSoC is open to <strong>students and newcomers to open-source development</strong>, making it an excellent opportunity for those looking to get involved with PostgreSQL. Whether you’re interested in database internals, extensions, drivers, performance tools, or UI development, there’s a place for you in the PostgreSQL ecosystem.</p> <p><strong>Key Dates:</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Mentoring organization applications are open now</strong> at <a href="https://g.co/gsoc">g.co/gsoc</a> and close <strong>February 11, 2025, at 18:00 UTC</strong>.</li> <li>If you’re interested in becoming a mentor, now is the time to reach out to us!</li> <li>It’s time to collect project ideas and update the <a href="https://wiki.postgresql.org/wiki/GSoC_2025">GSoC 2025 Ideas page</a>.</li> <li>Read the <a href="https://google.github.io/gsocguides/mentor/">GSoC Mentor Guide</a> for useful tips.</li> </ul> <h2 id="project-ideas-and-mentorship">Project Ideas and Mentorship</h2> <p>The <strong>most important part of our application as a mentoring organization</strong> is having a <strong>well-defined list of project ideas</strong>. These projects should take approximately:</p> <ul> <li><strong>90 hours</strong> (small project),</li> <li><strong>175 hours</strong> (medium project),</li> <li><strong>350 hours</strong> (large project).</li> </ul> <p>We encourage <strong>all PostgreSQL community members</strong> to submit project ideas and volunteer as mentors. Mentorship is essential for growing our community, sharing knowledge, and integrating new contributors into PostgreSQL development.</p> <h2 id="meet-us-at-fosdem">Meet Us at FOSDEM</h2> <p>Want to discuss project ideas or mentorship opportunities in person?<br/> <strong>Let’s talk during <a href="https://andreas.scherbaum.la/post/2025-01-20_postgresql-at-fosdem-2025/">FOSDEM</a> this week!</strong> PostgreSQL will have a booth and a devroom, so there will be plenty of opportunities to connect.</p> <p>Also, a few members of the <strong>Google Open Source team</strong> will be at FOSDEM carrying <strong>GSoC pennant flags and blue GSoC beanies</strong>. You can find them:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Upper level of Building K, near the large glass doors</strong></li> <li><strong>Saturday &amp; Sunday from 11:00–14:00</strong></li> </ul> <p>Stop by and say hi if you’re interested in GSoC!</p> <h2 id="apply-now--spread-the-word">Apply Now &amp; Spread the Word</h2> <p>As with last year, please consider PostgreSQL to be an <strong>“Umbrella”</strong> project, and anything that would be regarded as a <strong>“PostgreSQL Family”</strong> per the <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/about/policies/news-and-events/">News/Announce policy</a> is likely to be acceptable as a PostgreSQL GSoC project.</p> <p>In other words, if you’re a contributor or developer on WAL-G, barman, pgBackRest, pgwatch, pgagroal, pgexporter, pgmoneta, pgpool, pgbouncer, the PostgreSQL website (pgweb), the PgEU/PgUS website code (pgeu-system), pgAdmin4, DBeaver, HeidiSQL, pldebugger, pspg, the PG RPMs (pgrpms), the JDBC driver, the ODBC driver, or any of the many other PG Family projects, please feel free to add a project for consideration!</p> <p>We need:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Project ideas</strong> that fit the GSoC guidelines.</li> <li><strong>Mentors</strong> to help guide contributors.</li> <li><strong>New contributors</strong> looking to get involved.</li> <li><strong>Community support</strong> to spread awareness.</li> </ul> <h3 id="next-steps">Next Steps</h3> <ul> <li>Read the <a href="https://google.github.io/gsocguides/mentor/">GSoC Mentor Guide</a> and <a href="https://developers.google.com/open-source/gsoc/faq">FAQs</a>.</li> <li><strong>Encourage other open-source projects</strong> to apply! If you know of an open-source org that might be a good fit, remind them to check out the <a href="https://developers.google.com/open-source/gsoc/resources">GSoC resources</a> and use us as a reference.</li> </ul> <p>Let’s make GSoC 2025 another successful year for PostgreSQL and open-source innovation! 🚀</p> <p>Best regards,<br/> Pavlo Golub,<br/> on behalf of PostgreSQL GSoC Admins 💙💛</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="gsoc"/><category term="community"/><category term="postgresql"/><category term="personal"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Google Summer of Code is back for 2025!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PGDay/MED 2024 Napoli Edition</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgdaymed-2024-napoli-edition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PGDay/MED 2024 Napoli Edition"/><published>2024-12-17T08:51:54+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-17T08:51:54+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgdaymed-2024-napoli-edition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgdaymed-2024-napoli-edition/"><![CDATA[<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>The first-ever official PostgreSQL conference was held in Italy. Years later, PGDay/MED 2024 brought us back to this inspiring country. I was excited to visit Naples, often called the cradle of pizza and home to some of the finest cuisines in the world. As a self-proclaimed gastronomic geek, this was a bucket-list experience both professionally and personally!</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-conference-atmosphere">Conference Atmosphere</h2> <p>This was the second iteration of the Mediterranean PGDay series following Malta. We are still working hard to build strong events in this region as a community. Napoli’s conference was a one-track event with not so many attendees, creating a warm and cozy atmosphere. Each talk felt like a friendly discussion filled with comments, questions, and even jokes. It was a refreshing contrast to the larger, bustling conferences like PostgreSQL Europe or FOSDEM.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-the-venue">The Venue</h2> <p>The conference venue was perfectly located right in front of Naples’ Central Station. The entire top level of the hotel was divided into a lecture room and a restaurant. Adding to the charm was a beautiful terrace offering views of Mount Vesuvius and the sea. It was truly a spectacular setting.</p> <div class="wp-block-image"> <figure class="aligncenter"><a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_074253728-scaled.jpg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="300" height="169" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_074253728-300x169.jpg" alt="PgDay/MED Naples venue" class="wp-image-127715" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_074253728-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_074253728-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_074253728-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_074253728-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_074253728-2048x1152.jpg 2048w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_074253728-18x10.jpg 18w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_074253728-scaled.jpg 2560w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"/></a></figure></div> <p></p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-my-talk-wordle-in-postgresql">My Talk: Wordle in PostgreSQL</h2> <p>My presentation focused on implementing the Wordle game inside PostgreSQL. Given the location, I added an Italian vocabulary to the demo, allowing us to have some fun with the local attendees. It was a huge success! We even found a bug in the Italian Hunspell dictionary and another issue with the comparison functions during the demo. I included a few local-themed slides featuring Adriano Celentano and Pippo Franco for added flair. The audience laughed and snapped pictures, making me feel like a stand-up comedian. After this experience, I seriously consider writing a full database-themed stand-up routine. 😄</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-community-and-networking">Community and Networking</h2> <p>We had productive discussions with local community members about the future of PostgreSQL in the region. I don’t want to spoil anything, but I hope you’ll hear some exciting news soon from my friend <a href="https://postgresql.life/post/federico_campoli/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Federico Campoli</a>.</p> <div class="wp-block-image"> <figure class="aligncenter"><a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/1733408503134.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="800" height="450" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/1733408503134.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127733" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/1733408503134.jpg 800w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/1733408503134-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/1733408503134-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/1733408503134-18x10.jpg 18w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px"/></a></figure></div> <p><br/>I was also thrilled to see Fabiana Farias as a speaker. As a representative of the new generation of programmers, her talk provided a fresh perspective on the future of technology.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-exploring-naples">Exploring Naples</h2> <p>This event set a new world record for culinary indulgence! We visited the same nearby local restaurant three days in a row because the cuisine and staff were so amazing. We made it a mission to try every item on the menu, all paired with exquisite Southern Italian wines.</p> <figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-3 is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex"> <figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_121357913-scaled.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="127722" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_121357913-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127722" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_121357913-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_121357913-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_121357913-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_121357913-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_121357913-2048x1152.jpg 2048w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_121357913-18x10.jpg 18w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_121357913-scaled.jpg 2560w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure> <figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_083100051-scaled.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="576" height="1024" data-id="127721" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_083100051-576x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127721" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_083100051-576x1024.jpg 576w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_083100051-169x300.jpg 169w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_083100051-768x1365.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_083100051-864x1536.jpg 864w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_083100051-1152x2048.jpg 1152w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_083100051-7x12.jpg 7w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_083100051-scaled.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px"/></a></figure> <figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_125504870-scaled.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="127724" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_125504870-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127724" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_125504870-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_125504870-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_125504870-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_125504870-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_125504870-2048x1152.jpg 2048w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_125504870-18x10.jpg 18w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_125504870-scaled.jpg 2560w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure> <figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_122943523-scaled.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="127723" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_122943523-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127723" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_122943523-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_122943523-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_122943523-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_122943523-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_122943523-2048x1152.jpg 2048w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_122943523-18x10.jpg 18w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241208_122943523-scaled.jpg 2560w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure> <figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_185148157-scaled.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="576" height="1024" data-id="127720" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_185148157-576x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127720" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_185148157-576x1024.jpg 576w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_185148157-169x300.jpg 169w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_185148157-768x1365.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_185148157-864x1536.jpg 864w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_185148157-1152x2048.jpg 1152w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_185148157-7x12.jpg 7w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_185148157-scaled.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px"/></a></figure> <figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183330610-scaled.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="576" height="1024" data-id="127719" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183330610-576x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127719" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183330610-576x1024.jpg 576w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183330610-169x300.jpg 169w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183330610-768x1365.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183330610-864x1536.jpg 864w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183330610-1152x2048.jpg 1152w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183330610-7x12.jpg 7w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183330610-scaled.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px"/></a></figure> <figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183136240-scaled.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="576" height="1024" data-id="127718" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183136240-576x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127718" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183136240-576x1024.jpg 576w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183136240-169x300.jpg 169w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183136240-768x1365.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183136240-864x1536.jpg 864w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183136240-1152x2048.jpg 1152w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183136240-7x12.jpg 7w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241205_183136240-scaled.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px"/></a></figure> </figure> <p>After the conference, some of us explored the archaeological excavations of Pompeii—a fascinating glimpse into history.</p> <figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls="" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_112722384.TS-CINEMATIC_MOMENT_VIDEO.mp4"></video></figure> <figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-2 is-cropped wp-block-gallery-2 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex"> <figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="127727" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110038063-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127727" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110038063-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110038063-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110038063-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110038063-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110038063-2048x1152.jpg 2048w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110038063-18x10.jpg 18w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110038063-scaled.jpg 2560w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></figure> <figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-id="127728" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110044881-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127728" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110044881-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110044881-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110044881-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110044881-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110044881-2048x1152.jpg 2048w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110044881-18x10.jpg 18w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/PXL_20241206_110044881-scaled.jpg 2560w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></figure> </figure> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-reflections-on-the-mediterranean-series">Reflections on the Mediterranean Series</h2> <p>I absolutely love the concept of Mediterranean PostgreSQL conferences! While there are challenges with organising teams and schedules, we can overcome them in the coming years. I hope PostgreSQL Europe continues to support this event and gives it more attention. At the same time, it’s up to us as a community to put in the effort to make these events shine.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2> <p>PGDay/MED 2024 in Naples was a testament to the exceptional charm of smaller, local conferences. These events provide a welcoming atmosphere where everyone can connect on a deeper level, share insights, and build lasting relationships. Local community events like these are vital for the global growth of PostgreSQL.</p> <p>I invite you to join us at the next PGDay/MED. Let’s continue celebrating the Mediterranean spirit, sharing knowledge, and growing our amazing community together!</p> <p>The post <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en/pgday-med-2024-napoli-edition/">PGDay/MED 2024 Napoli Edition</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en">CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this blog posting Pavlo Golub will tell you more about his trip to the PGDay Napoli on the 5th of December. The post PGDay/MED 2024 Napoli Edition appeared first on CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">vip-manager v2.8 meets Patroni REST API</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/vip-manager-v28-meets-patroni-rest-api/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="vip-manager v2.8 meets Patroni REST API"/><published>2024-11-28T09:01:31+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-28T09:01:31+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/vip-manager-v28-meets-patroni-rest-api</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/vip-manager-v28-meets-patroni-rest-api/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/cybertec-postgresql/vip-manager" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vip-manager</a> has long been a crucial tool for managing virtual IPs in PostgreSQL HA setups, providing reliable leader routing. With the release of <a href="https://github.com/cybertec-postgresql/vip-manager/releases" target="_blank" rel="noopener">version 2.8.0</a>, we're taking things to the next level by introducing native integration with the Patroni <a href="https://patroni.readthedocs.io/en/latest/rest_api.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">REST API</a>. This new feature adds flexibility and simplifies configuration, making it easier than ever to manage your PostgreSQL HA clusters.</p> <h2>Main Feature: Patroni REST API Integration</h2> <p>In this release, <code>vip-manager</code> can now directly interact with Patroni via its REST API. This integration removes the need for complex custom setups, enabling more dynamic and flexible management of virtual IPs.</p> <h3>What does this mean for you?</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Native Integration</strong>: <code>vip-manager</code> now works seamlessly with Patroni clusters without additional configurations for <code>etcd</code> or <code>consul</code>.</li> <li><strong>Huge Flexibility</strong>: The tool isn't limited to managing virtual IPs for primary nodes anymore; it can also handle replicas.</li> <li><strong>Simplified Configuration</strong>: With default values in place (e.g., localhost for DCS endpoints), setting up <code>vip-manager</code> is quicker and easier than ever.</li> </ul> <h2>Example Usage of Patroni REST API</h2> <p>Here are a couple of examples to showcase the new feature:</p> <h3>Managing Virtual IP for the Primary Node</h3> <p>This command configures <code>vip-manager</code> to set up a virtual IP for the primary node:</p> <pre class="urvanov-syntax-highlighter-plain-tag">vip-manager --ip=10.0.0.42 --interface=eth0 \ 
--trigger-key="/leader" --trigger-value=200 --dcs-type=patroni</pre> <p><strong>What does it do?</strong></p> <ul> <li><code>--ip=10.0.0.42</code>: The virtual IP to be managed.</li> <li><code>--interface=eth0</code>: The network interface where vip-manager will set up the virtual IP.</li> <li><code>--trigger-key="/leader"</code>: The endpoint in Patroni's REST API to check if the node is the leader.</li> <li><code>--trigger-value=200</code>: The HTTP status code indicating success.</li> <li><code>--dcs-type=patroni</code>: Specifies Patroni as the source of truth (the prefix <code>dcs</code> is still here due to historical reasons).</li> </ul> <p>If the current host is the leader, according to Patroni, the virtual IP will be assigned.</p> <h3>Managing Virtual IP for the Replica</h3> <p>This command configures <code>vip-manager</code> to manage a virtual IP for the replica node:</p> <pre class="urvanov-syntax-highlighter-plain-tag">vip-manager --ip=10.0.0.42 --interface=eth0 \
 --trigger-key="/asynchronous" --trigger-value=200 --dcs-type=patroni</pre> <p><strong>Key Notes:</strong></p> <ul> <li>No need to set <code>dcs-endpoints</code> if Patroni is running on localhost.</li> <li>Flexibility to manage virtual IPs for nodes other than the primary, like replicas.</li> </ul> <h2>Try it today!</h2> <p>If you want to contribute to <strong>vip-manager</strong> and help to make it better:</p> <ul> <li>⭐<a href="https://github.com/cybertec-postgresql/vip-manager/stargazers">give a star</a> to the project,</li> <li>feel free to open an 🤚<a href="https://github.com/cybertec-postgresql/vip-manager/issues">issue</a> and ask a 🎓<a href="https://github.com/cybertec-postgresql/vip-manager/discussions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">question</a></li> <li>or even consider submitting a 📜<a href="https://github.com/cybertec-postgresql/vip-manager/pulls" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pull request</a>.</li> </ul> <p>In conclusion, I wish you all the best! Happy managing! 💙💛<br/> See you soon in person at one of the <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/about/events/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">conferences</a>, meetups, or <a href="/en/training/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">training sessions!</a></p> <p>The post <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en/vip-manager-meets-patroni-rest-api/">vip-manager v2.8 meets Patroni REST API</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en">CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this blog posting you will read more about the vip-manager and Patroni and what are the advantage of it. The post vip-manager v2.8 meets Patroni REST API appeared first on CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PGDay Lowlands 2024 Reflections</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgday-lowlands-2024-reflections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PGDay Lowlands 2024 Reflections"/><published>2024-10-15T05:13:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-15T05:13:01+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgday-lowlands-2024-reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgday-lowlands-2024-reflections/"><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"> <figure class="aligncenter"><img decoding="async" width="2048" height="1363" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/PavloGolub-PGDay-Amsterdam.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127049" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/PavloGolub-PGDay-Amsterdam.jpg 2048w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/PavloGolub-PGDay-Amsterdam-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/PavloGolub-PGDay-Amsterdam-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/PavloGolub-PGDay-Amsterdam-768x511.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/PavloGolub-PGDay-Amsterdam-1536x1022.jpg 1536w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/PavloGolub-PGDay-Amsterdam-18x12.jpg 18w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px"/></figure></div> <p></p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>This year, <a href="https://2024.pgday.nl/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PGDay Lowlands 2024</a> was paired with <a href="https://2024.pgday.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PGDay UK 2024</a>, which gave me the chance to try something new—taking the train directly from London to Amsterdam. Naturally, I was curious about passing through the famous tunnel under La Manche (some folks call it the English Channel, but I am still unsure why 😜). Spoiler alert: there's nothing cool to see, just darkness. 🙂</p> <p>If you want to read about PGDay UK 2024, I recommend <a href="https://dataegret.com/2024/09/back-from-pgday-uk-2024/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the blog post</a> of my friend Stefan Fercot. Thank God he did a great job, so I can focus only on one event instead of two! 😅</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-a-special-connection-with-amsterdam">A Special Connection with Amsterdam</h2> <p>PGDay Lowlands 2024 marks the first year of this event, but Amsterdam holds a special place in my professional journey. My first ever PostgreSQL community conference was in this beautiful city, way back in 2011, during <a href="https://2011.pgconf.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pgconf.eu</a>. So, Amsterdam isn't just another city for me; it's a key part of my community and professional life. I always love coming back here.</p> <p>The conference schedule was pretty packed, so I only had a little time to visit my favorite places in Amsterdam this time. But the experience of the conference itself made up for that.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-my-talk-customizing-the-wordle-game-experience-with-postgresql">My Talk: "Customizing the Wordle Game Experience with PostgreSQL"</h2> <p>My presentation was titled "Customizing the Wordle Game Experience with PostgreSQL." Despite the fun name, the talk covered some serious and interesting topics, like full-text search dictionaries and customizing psql. The best part? We ended the talk by playing Wordle with the audience, where they had to guess PostgreSQL 5-letter keywords. I'm happy to report that <a href="https://postgresql.life/post/gianni_ciolli/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gianni Ciolli</a> is officially the best keyword professional among us! 😄</p> <div class="wp-block-image"> <figure class="aligncenter"><img decoding="async" width="2048" height="1363" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Wordle-PGDay-Amsterdam.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127051" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Wordle-PGDay-Amsterdam.jpg 2048w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Wordle-PGDay-Amsterdam-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Wordle-PGDay-Amsterdam-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Wordle-PGDay-Amsterdam-768x511.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Wordle-PGDay-Amsterdam-1536x1022.jpg 1536w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Wordle-PGDay-Amsterdam-18x12.jpg 18w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px"/></figure></div> <p></p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-a-second-chance">A Second Chance</h2> <p>I initially presented this talk once at PgConf in New York, but unfortunately, my slot was in parallel with <a href="https://postgresql.life/post/bruce_momjian/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bruce Momjian's</a> session. Naturally, many attendees chose to go to his talk (honestly, I would have done the same!). That left me with little feedback and some doubts about the talk's appeal. So, I'm incredibly thankful to the PGDay Lowlands Call for Papers <a href="https://2024.pgday.nl/organisation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">committee</a> for giving me a second chance! It was such a relief to see that the audience loved it and to have great questions and discussions afterward.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-a-friendly-and-perfect-atmosphere">A Friendly and Perfect Atmosphere</h2> <p>The atmosphere at PGDay Lowlands was perfect—so friendly! One of the aspects I loved the most was having a meetup the day before the main event. It was the perfect opportunity to get to know the venue, meet some other speakers, and get into the conference mood. It was a brilliant idea, and I hope it becomes a tradition.</p> <p>I met many old friends and, of course, many new faces. It's always refreshing to reconnect with familiar people while getting to know new community members.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-memorable-talks">Memorable Talks</h2> <p>All the talks were great, including the lightning talks. Still, one session stood out for its humor and creativity: <a href="https://www.postgresql.eu/events/pgdaynl2024/schedule/session/5967-postgresql-high-availability-poker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">"PostgreSQL High Availability Poker."</a> The speakers took on roles like actors in a theater, and it was honestly one of the best comedies I've ever seen at a conference! It brought a unique and entertaining twist to the event.</p> <div class="wp-block-image"> <figure class="aligncenter"><img decoding="async" width="2048" height="1362" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Poker-PGDay-Amsterdam.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127053" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Poker-PGDay-Amsterdam.jpg 2048w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Poker-PGDay-Amsterdam-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Poker-PGDay-Amsterdam-1024x681.jpg 1024w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Poker-PGDay-Amsterdam-768x511.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Poker-PGDay-Amsterdam-1536x1022.jpg 1536w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Poker-PGDay-Amsterdam-18x12.jpg 18w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px"/></figure></div> <p></p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-the-venue-was-amazing">The Venue Was Amazing</h2> <p>The conference was held at an amazing venue! I absolutely loved the stage with a couch on it—it felt so relaxed yet professional. The side monitors displaying Mastodon feeds and additional conference information were also great. I was especially impressed with the AV team. They were incredibly attentive, ensuring every speaker was fully prepared with mics before stepping on stage.</p> <p>PGDay Lowlands 2024 is easily one of the best PostgreSQL conferences I've ever attended. Next year, I hope they'll include a little local flavor — perhaps some Dutch cuisine like herring on the tables? 😉</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-the-growing-postgresql-community">The Growing PostgreSQL Community</h2> <p>The PostgreSQL community is growing steadily, and it's heartwarming to see. More meetups, more events—it's a true sign of progress. It's such a pleasure to witness this growth and be part of it.</p> <p>Local events like PGDay Lowlands are significant for the global growth of PostgreSQL. These smaller regional gatherings lay the groundwork for more extensive global initiatives. They help foster stronger connections within local communities.</p> <p>I'm already looking forward to the next PGDay Lowlands! The organizers are working on securing another excellent venue for next year, and I'm sure it will be another fantastic event.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-exhausted-but-satisfied">Exhausted But Satisfied</h2> <p>After a week of traveling and attending two major conferences, I was definitely exhausted. Traveling is more challenging than it used to be when I was younger! But at the same time, I felt a deep sense of satisfaction. We accomplished so much, and it was all worth it.</p> <div class="wp-block-image"> <figure class="aligncenter"><img decoding="async" width="2048" height="1363" src="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Cybertec-PGDay-Amsterdam.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-127055" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Cybertec-PGDay-Amsterdam.jpg 2048w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Cybertec-PGDay-Amsterdam-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Cybertec-PGDay-Amsterdam-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Cybertec-PGDay-Amsterdam-768x511.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Cybertec-PGDay-Amsterdam-1536x1022.jpg 1536w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Cybertec-PGDay-Amsterdam-18x12.jpg 18w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px"/></figure></div> <p></p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-more-exciting-events-on-the-horizon">More Exciting Events on the Horizon</h2> <p>For me, there are still three crucial PostgreSQL events left this year:</p> <ul class="wp-block-list"> <li><a href="https://2024.pgconf.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PostgreSQL Europe Conference</a> in Athens</li> <li><a href="https://passdatacommunitysummit.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PASS Data Community Summit</a> in Seattle</li> <li><a href="https://2024.pgdaymed.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PGDay/MED</a> in Napoli</li> </ul> <p>I'm excited to see what's in store at each of these incredible events! See you there!</p> <p>The post <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en/pgday-lowlands-2024-reflections/">PGDay Lowlands 2024 Reflections</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en">CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Check out Pavlo's reflections on PGDay Lowlands 2024, including his talk about "Customizing the Wordle Game Experience with PostgreSQL" and full-text search dictionaries. The post PGDay Lowlands 2024 Reflections appeared first on CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PGDay Hyderabad 2024 Reflections</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgday-hyderabad-2024-reflections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PGDay Hyderabad 2024 Reflections"/><published>2024-09-24T06:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-24T06:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgday-hyderabad-2024-reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgday-hyderabad-2024-reflections/"><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image"> <figure class="aligncenter"><img decoding="async" width="1280" height="720" src="/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1725001366931.jpg" alt="Pavlo Golub rocking the show talking about the super important topic - monitoring Professional PostgreSQL monitoring made easy" class="wp-image-126558" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1725001366931.jpg 1280w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1725001366931-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1725001366931-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1725001366931-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1725001366931-18x10.jpg 18w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px"/></figure></div> <p></p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>As a senior database consultant and developer at CYBERTEC PostgreSQL International, I enjoyed speaking at <a href="https://pghyd.in/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PGDay Hyderabad 2024</a>. This event marked two firsts for me: my first time visiting India and the first-ever PostgreSQL conference held in Hyderabad. I was filled with excitement and curiosity as I started this journey. I didn't know what to expect, but I was eager to experience it all.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-arrival-and-first-impressions">Arrival and first Impressions</h2> <p>I arrived in Hyderabad late at night, around 2:00 AM. While I was a little tired from the long flight, I was extremely excited.. However, I made two rookie mistakes. First, I didn't buy a local SIM card, which left me without mobile internet for the whole trip — a particularly unpleasant experience in India, where OTPs are required even for something as simple as Uber. Second, I didn't exchange money for local currency, leading to small logistical challenges. And the driving culture? Well, let's just say that seeing it live was a real surprise! 😱😅</p> <p>Being in India for the first time was a cultural shock — but in a good way! Everything here is different from what you're used to in Europe. The tempo of life is wild, and the cuisine is an adventure of its own. Yes, it's spicy, but I handled it! If you ever have the opportunity to visit India, please do so. It's an unforgettable experience.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-exploring-hyderabad">Exploring Hyderabad</h2> <p>Despite the rain pouring down the entire day, I was glad I took a full-day tour of Hyderabad. I visited Golconda Fort, The Charminar, Laad Bazaar, and Mecca Masjid Mosque. One of the highlights was stopping at the famous Nimrah Cafe, where the owner welcomed me and gave me a kitchen tour. I sampled an assortment of delicious pastries and tasted their renowned tea. Spending time there, soaking in the atmosphere, was a beautiful experience. I highly recommend it!</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-my-first-pgday-in-india">My First PGDay in India</h2> <p>In general I had no particular expectations at my first PostgreSQL conference in India. I just wanted to live in the moment and take everything in as it unfolded. Of course I was curious how the Indian community would receive my talk, "Professional PostgreSQL Monitoring Made Easy," which I've presented many times before.</p> <p>I was happy to see the full room for my talk. The audience was incredibly engaged, and I received several clever and interesting questions. The highlight of my experience came afterward when two attendees approached me to show how they used PGWatch in their workflows. They drastically improved their Grafana dashboards, and their work was so impressive that I immediately encouraged them to open-source it! These moments remind me why I love being part of this vibrant, innovative community.</p> <p>The atmosphere at PGDay Hyderabad was special, at least for me. People in India are incredibly kind and peaceful. It's hard to put the differences between this and other conferences I've attended in Europe or elsewhere. You just need to visit India and experience it for yourself!</p> <p>I had the chance to meet many local PostgreSQL community members, which was fantastic. Some of them I had met at previous events, while others I knew from online interactions or through working with CYBERTEC on various projects. It was heartwarming to hear such positive feedback about my colleagues, particularly Ants Aasma.</p> <p>India is making great strides in diversity within its PostgreSQL community. I had the pleasure of speaking with representatives from "Postgres Women India," who are doing wonderful work to promote inclusion.</p> <p>As is my habit, I only attended a few talks on the day of my presentation. Before my talk, there's always some pressure, and after, I tend to be exhausted. It's hard to remember much from talks that day, except for the incredible interactions with attendees.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-conference-venue-and-organization">Conference Venue and Organization</h2> <p>The conference occurred in the VAJRA-C4 building at the IIIT-Hyderabad Campus, and tickets were sold out weeks in advance! The venue was well-suited for this year's event, but they'll need a larger space with such a high demand for next year.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-discovering-a-growing-postgresql-community">Discovering a Growing PostgreSQL Community</h2> <p>The audience was warm and welcoming to all the speakers. It was a pleasure to present to such an engaged group. India's PostgreSQL community is growing rapidly, and I'm thrilled to have become a part of it. I'm excited to see how this community will continue to evolve and thrive. Local PostgreSQL communities are the backbone of the global ecosystem. Meetups and smaller local groups lay the foundation for larger events like PGDay and PGConf. They play an essential role in driving PostgreSQL adoption and innovation.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-looking-forward-to-future-events">Looking Forward to Future Events</h2> <p>I had an amazing time at PGDay Hyderabad. I'm already looking forward to <a href="https://pgconf.in/conferences/pgconfin2025" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PGConf India 2025</a>, which will occur in Bengaluru in March. I'd also love to attend other PostgreSQL events, for example, in Australia and Japan in the future.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>I'd like to thank the organizers, sponsors, and everyone who attended PGDay Hyderabad 2024. It was a fantastic experience, and I can't wait to see what the future holds for PostgreSQL in India and beyond. Until next time, happy Postgres-ing! 🖖</p> <p>The post <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en/pgday-hyderabad-2024-reflections/">PGDay Hyderabad 2024 Reflections</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en">CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this blog, I would like to tell you more about PGDay Hyderabad 2024. It was my first PostgreSQL conference in India. Find out more... The post PGDay Hyderabad 2024 Reflections appeared first on CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Remote Sinks in pgwatch3 by Akshat Jaimini</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/remote-sinks-in-pgwatch3-by-akshat-jaimini/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Remote Sinks in pgwatch3 by Akshat Jaimini"/><published>2024-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/remote-sinks-in-pgwatch3-by-akshat-jaimini</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/remote-sinks-in-pgwatch3-by-akshat-jaimini/"><![CDATA[<p>As a mentor for Google Summer of Code (GSoC) 2024, I am thrilled to witness the innovative ideas and technical expertise that young minds bring to the table. This year, I have the pleasure of working with Akshat Jaimini on an exciting project that aims to enhance PostgreSQL monitoring through the development of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/programs/2024/projects/fA8SxpN7">RPC sinks for pgwatch3</a>. Akshat's work focuses on extending pgwatch3 by developing a mechanism to allow Remote Procedure Call (RPC) sinks, which will offer more flexibility and integration possibilities for users.</p> <p>At this point, I would like to hand over to Akshat, who will delve into the specifics of the project, its goals, and the challenges we aim to address. Akshat, the floor is yours!</p> <hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/> <div class="wp-block-image"> <figure class="alignright"><img decoding="async" width="128" height="128" src="/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Akshat.png" alt="" class="wp-image-126104" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Akshat.png 128w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Akshat-12x12.png 12w" sizes="(max-width: 128px) 100vw, 128px"/></figure></div> <p></p> <p>Hello! I am Akshat Jaimini, a Computer Engineering Student from India. I was a part of PostgreSQL for the Google Summer of Code 2023 Program where I worked closely with the pgweb development team on developing a testing harness suite for the Official PostgreSQL website. Excited to be a part of the PostgreSQL community!</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-sinks">Sinks?</h2> <p>pgwatch v3 is well under works and with that comes the possibility of new and awesome features that were not there earlier. One such feature is the addition of ‘Remote Sinks’ in this awesome tool.<br/>Sinks…?</p> <p>Well if you have used pgwatch2 earlier, you would be familiar with the storage concept. Let me get you up to speed.</p> <p>Previously we configured pgwatch in two ways: the Push and the Pull configs. First one will send store measurements somewhere directly, while the pull config allows scrapers to fetch measurements from pgwatch.</p> <p>Regardless of the config being used, essentially all your metric measurements need to be stored somewhere. That particular ‘storage unit’ is referred to as a Sink in pgwatch v3.</p> <p>So basically pgwatch fetches metric measurements from the ‘Source’ Database and sends/stores them in ‘Sinks’.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-why-remote-sinks">Why Remote Sinks?</h2> <p>Till now pgwatch supported PostgreSQL, JSON file and Prometheus as the possible sink solutions. Although these are great for the primary use case but they fall short when these metrics are required for something more.</p> <p>Although these new formats can be added as the feature requests come in, but why keep the capability to ourselves? So we introduced the concept of Remote Sinks which basically provides you with an interface using the go RPC library to get the metrics measurements as a stream of data and utilize them for your respective use cases. This project is a part of Google Summer Of Code, 2024.</p> <p>So the users get an option to write any type of sink without worrying about if pgwatch will be able to integrate with it.</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-architecture">Architecture</h2> <p>As I mentioned earlier, we decided to go with the default RPC library that comes in Go. To visualize this we can refer to the following diagrams:</p> <figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="881" height="537" src="/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/pgwatch-rpc-sinks-architecture.png" alt="" class="wp-image-126099" srcset="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/pgwatch-rpc-sinks-architecture.png 881w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/pgwatch-rpc-sinks-architecture-300x183.png 300w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/pgwatch-rpc-sinks-architecture-768x468.png 768w, https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/pgwatch-rpc-sinks-architecture-18x12.png 18w" sizes="(max-width: 881px) 100vw, 881px"/></figure> <p>There are some key takeaways from the architecture above:</p> <ul class="wp-block-list"> <li>Remote sinks can be called via a single Remote Procedure Call, therefore no additional processing required.</li> <li>pgwatch does not care about the details of the remote sink at the back.</li> <li>No additional changes required in pgwatch3 setup.</li> </ul> <p>To use your remote sinks you can simply run:</p> <pre class="urvanov-syntax-highlighter-plain-tag">pgwatch --sink=rpc://somehost:42/foo ...</pre> <p>You can try out the development build on <a href="https://github.com/destrex271/pgwatch3_rpc_server">GitHub</a>.</p> <p>As of now&nbsp;the demo supports the following output formats: CSV and Parquet. And we plan on adding more examples for our users but that's a surprise we’ll like to keep for <a href="https://www.postgresql.eu/events/pgconfeu2024/schedule/session/5647-gsoc-2024-enhancing-data-insights-for-postgres-with-remote-sinks/">pgconf.eu 2024</a> 😉</p> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-how-can-i-develop-my-own-sinks">How can I develop my own sinks?</h2> <p>To develop your own sinks you can follow the given steps.</p> <p>Clone the repository from https://github.com/destrex271/pgwatch3_rpc_server</p> <p>In the sinks folder create a new file with whatever sink format name you want and declare an enum for your sink in the <span id="urvanov-syntax-highlighter-67a7473c9b87d371582530" class="urvanov-syntax-highlighter-syntax urvanov-syntax-highlighter-syntax-inline crayon-theme-vs2012-copy crayon-theme-vs2012-copy-inline urvanov-syntax-highlighter-font-sourcecodepro" style="font-size: 14px !important; line-height: 16px !important;font-size: 14px !important;"><span class="crayon-pre urvanov-syntax-highlighter-code" style="font-size: 14px !important; line-height: 16px !important;font-size: 14px !important; -moz-tab-size:4; -o-tab-size:4; -webkit-tab-size:4; tab-size:4;">sink<span class="crayon-o">/</span>types.go</span></span>&nbsp; file. Also don’t forget to update the conditionals! (We’ll end up changing this so that it automatically prepares calls according to the enums in the future)</p> <p>With this your setup is complete!</p> <p>PS: You can raise a PR if you feel that these sinks can be used by other people too!</p> <p>While developing your sinks you can use the <span id="urvanov-syntax-highlighter-67a7473c9b87f832652432" class="urvanov-syntax-highlighter-syntax urvanov-syntax-highlighter-syntax-inline crayon-theme-vs2012-copy crayon-theme-vs2012-copy-inline urvanov-syntax-highlighter-font-sourcecodepro" style="font-size: 14px !important; line-height: 16px !important;font-size: 14px !important;"><span class="crayon-pre urvanov-syntax-highlighter-code" style="font-size: 14px !important; line-height: 16px !important;font-size: 14px !important; -moz-tab-size:4; -o-tab-size:4; -webkit-tab-size:4; tab-size:4;">primary_receiver</span></span>&nbsp; instance passed into the <span id="urvanov-syntax-highlighter-67a7473c9b880388801254" class="urvanov-syntax-highlighter-syntax urvanov-syntax-highlighter-syntax-inline crayon-theme-vs2012-copy crayon-theme-vs2012-copy-inline urvanov-syntax-highlighter-font-sourcecodepro" style="font-size: 14px !important; line-height: 16px !important;font-size: 14px !important;"><span class="crayon-pre urvanov-syntax-highlighter-code" style="font-size: 14px !important; line-height: 16px !important;font-size: 14px !important; -moz-tab-size:4; -o-tab-size:4; -webkit-tab-size:4; tab-size:4;">UpdateMeasurement()</span></span>&nbsp; function of your sink for the following:</p> <ul class="wp-block-list"> <li>Retrieving Meta parameters associated with the Remote Procedure Call.</li> <li>Receiving Sync Metric Signals(Like ‘DELETE monitored database’, ‘ADD new metric’, etc…) if you want to support them in your sinks.</li> </ul> <h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="h-how-do-i-test-my-sink">How do I test my sink?</h2> <p>Worry not, I have a dummy client written within the repository which you can use to generate requests for your newly developed sink. It is there to simulate pgwatch3 without actually launching an instance.<br/>Road Ahead!</p> <p>The development on this part of pgwatch3 is in full swing and we hope to soon make it as easily accessible for all our beloved users!</p> <p>Also if you wish to contribute let’s meet in the <a href="https://github.com/destrex271/pgwatch3_rpc_server/issues">discussions/issues section of the project.</a></p> <p>Thanks for reading!</p> <p><strong>In order to receive regular updates on important changes in PostgreSQL, <a href="/en/newsletter/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subscribe to our newsletter</a>, or follow us on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cybertec.postgresql" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Facebook</a> or <a href="https://at.linkedin.com/company/cybertec-postgresql" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">LinkedIn</a>.</strong></p> <p>The post <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en/remote-sinks-in-pgwatch3-by-akshat-jaimini/">Remote Sinks in pgwatch3 by Akshat Jaimini</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en">CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have the pleasure of working on an project that aims to enhance PostgreSQL monitoring through the development of RPC sinks for pgwatch3. The post Remote Sinks in pgwatch3 by Akshat Jaimini appeared first on CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to use PostgreSQL for (military) geoanalytics tasks by Taras Klioba</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/taras-klioba-postgis-in-warfare/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to use PostgreSQL for (military) geoanalytics tasks by Taras Klioba"/><published>2024-03-05T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-05T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/taras-klioba-postgis-in-warfare</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/taras-klioba-postgis-in-warfare/"><![CDATA[<p>During the <a href="https://www.postgresql.eu/events/pgconfeu2023/schedule/session/4605-from-map-to-reality-using-postgis-in-warfare/">PGConf.EU 2023</a>, my friend, colleague, and PostgreSQL Ukraine co-founder <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kloba/">Taras Klioba</a> delved into the fascinating intersection of geospatial analysis and modern warfare.</p> <p>He decided not to publish a video record of his talk for obvious reasons. But now, he has shared the essential details of his talk in the form of a <a href="https://klioba.com/how-to-use-postgresql-for-military-geoanalytics-tasks">blog article</a>. I want to boost this blog post for all Planet Postgres readers; that’s the primary purpose of the text you’re reading.</p> <p>Taras’s article discusses the importance of geoanalytics in military operations due to the prevalence of geospatial data, focusing on utilizing PostgreSQL to process such data. It addresses everyday geoanalytical tasks such as finding K-nearest objects, distance calculations, and point within a polygon determination. It aims to provide practical examples and tips. Open-source data, specifically russian military facility data from <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a>, is used as a primary dataset. It is then imported into PostgreSQL using the <a href="https://osm2pgsql.org/">osm2pgsql</a> tool for analysis and optimization.</p> <p>Additionally, fire data from NASA satellites is introduced as a second data source, sourced from the <a href="https://www.earthdata.nasa.gov/learn/find-data/near-real-time/firms/vj114imgtdlnrt">Fire Information for Resource Management System</a> (FIRMS). FIRMS allows real-time monitoring of active fires worldwide, including within russian military facilities’ territory since 2022. The process involves downloading fire data using a specific script and importing it into a PostgreSQL database for further analysis.</p> <p>For example, the text outlines a task of finding the K-nearest neighbors, precisely ten fires near the Shahed production plant in russia, known for manufacturing Iranian Shahed drones. It refers to previous <a href="https://molfar.com/blog/alabuga-deanon">research by the Molfar team</a> for detailed information about the factory, located in the special economic zone Alabuga in Tatarstan. The text highlights the shift in factory priorities towards drone production following sanctions. It proposes a method involving creating a buffer around the target area and recursively expanding it until the desired results are obtained.</p> <p>Please, read and share! Glory to Ukraine! 💙💛</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="postgis"/><category term="pgconf"/><category term="postgresql"/><category term="personal"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[During the PGConf.EU 2023, my friend, colleague, and PostgreSQL Ukraine co-founder Taras Klioba delved into the fascinating intersection of geospatial analysis and modern warfare. He decided not to publish a video record of his talk for obvious reasons. But now, he has shared the essential details of his talk in the form of a blog article. I want to boost this blog post for all Planet Postgres readers; that's the primary purpose of the text you're reading.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">pgxmock v4 is out! Mocking batches for PostgreSQL in Go!</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgxmock-v4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="pgxmock v4 is out! Mocking batches for PostgreSQL in Go!"/><published>2024-03-05T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-05T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgxmock-v4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/pgxmock-v4/"><![CDATA[<p>I am excited to announce the update of <strong><a href="https://github.com/pashagolub/pgxmock/releases/">pgxmock v4</a></strong>! This update adds long awaited support for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pgx.Batch</code> and completely rewrites the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Prepare</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Deallocate</code> mocking implementation.</p> <h2 id="what-are-batches">What are Batches?</h2> <p><a href="https://pkg.go.dev/github.com/jackc/pgx/v5#Batch">Batch queries</a> in <strong>pgx</strong> are a way of bundling multiple queries together to avoid unnecessary network round trips. A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Batch</code> must only be sent once. One can define a function to deal with the results of every query, e.g.</p> <div class="language-go highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">batch</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">pgx</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Batch</span><span class="p">{}</span>
  <span class="n">batch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Queue</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"select some_func()"</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">QueryRow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">func</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">row</span> <span class="n">pgx</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Row</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="kt">error</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="kt">int32</span>
    <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="n">row</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Scan</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="no">nil</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">err</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="n">fmt</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">err</span>
  <span class="p">})</span>

  <span class="n">batch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Queue</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"select * from foo*"</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Query</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">func</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">rows</span> <span class="n">pgx</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Rows</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="kt">error</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="c">// ...</span>
  <span class="p">})</span>

  <span class="n">batch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Queue</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"update foo set bar = 'zoo' where id = 1"</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Exec</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">func</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ct</span> <span class="n">pgconn</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">CommandTag</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">err</span> <span class="kt">error</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">ct</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">RowsAffected</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="m">1</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">errors</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">New</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"expected 1 row to be affected"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="k">return</span>
  <span class="p">})</span>

  <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">conn</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">SendBatch</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ctx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">batch</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Close</span><span class="p">()</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>If a developer wants to have more control over result checking, they can use explicit way. This way the example above transforms to</p> <div class="language-go highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>  <span class="n">batch</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">pgx</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Batch</span><span class="p">{}</span>
  <span class="n">batch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Queue</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"select some_func()"</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="n">batch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Queue</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"select * from foo*"</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="n">batch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Queue</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"update foo set bar = 'zoo' where id = 1"</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="n">br</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="n">mock</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">SendBatch</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ctx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">batch</span><span class="p">)</span>

  <span class="c">// process results</span>
  <span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="kt">int32</span>
  <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="n">br</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">QueryRow</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Scan</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="no">nil</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nb">panic</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">err</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="n">fmt</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">)</span>

  <span class="n">rows</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="n">br</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Query</span><span class="p">()</span>
  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="no">nil</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nb">panic</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">err</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="c">// ... process rows here</span>

  <span class="n">ct</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="n">br</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Exec</span><span class="p">()</span>
  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="no">nil</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nb">panic</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">err</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">!</span><span class="n">ct</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Update</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="m">1</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="n">ct</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">RowsAffected</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="n">fmt</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"something bad happened"</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>

  <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="n">br</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Close</span><span class="p">()</span>
  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="no">nil</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nb">panic</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">err</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="and-how-am-i-supposed-to-test-batches-with-pgxmock">And how am I supposed to test batches with pgxmock?</h2> <p>Really simple. Just as everything else. First, you define you expectations! Second, you call your function with a mock as an argument! And finally, you check if all expectations were met and if your code reacted as expected.</p> <p>Let’s imagine we have a function to test</p> <div class="language-go highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">func</span> <span class="n">processBatch</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">db</span> <span class="n">pgx</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Tx</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="n">err</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="n">batch</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">pgx</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Batch</span><span class="p">{}</span>
  <span class="n">batch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Queue</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"select 1 + 1"</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">QueryRow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">func</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">row</span> <span class="n">pgx</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Row</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="kt">error</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">var</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="kt">int32</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">row</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Scan</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">})</span>
  <span class="n">batch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Queue</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"update users set active = $1 where id = $2"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="no">true</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="m">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Exec</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">func</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ct</span> <span class="n">pgconn</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">CommandTag</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">err</span> <span class="kt">error</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">ct</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">RowsAffected</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="m">1</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">errors</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">New</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"expected 1 row to be affected"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="k">return</span>
  <span class="p">})</span>
  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">db</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">SendBatch</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ctx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">batch</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Close</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="k">func</span> <span class="n">TestBatch</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">t</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="n">testing</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">T</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="n">t</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Parallel</span><span class="p">()</span>
  <span class="n">mock</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">_</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="n">NewConn</span><span class="p">()</span>
  <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="n">assert</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">New</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">t</span><span class="p">)</span>

  <span class="c">// define our expectations</span>
  <span class="n">eb</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="n">mock</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">ExpectBatch</span><span class="p">()</span>
  <span class="n">eb</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">ExpectQuery</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"select"</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">WillReturnRows</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">NewRows</span><span class="p">([]</span><span class="kt">string</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="s">"sum"</span><span class="p">})</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">AddRow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="m">2</span><span class="p">))</span>
  <span class="n">eb</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">ExpectExec</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"update"</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">WithArgs</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="no">true</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="m">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">WillReturnResult</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">NewResult</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"UPDATE"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="m">1</span><span class="p">))</span>

  <span class="c">// run the test</span>
  <span class="n">err</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="n">processBatch</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">mock</span><span class="p">)</span>

  <span class="c">// check our expectations and code behaviour</span>
  <span class="n">a</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">NoError</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">err</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="n">a</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">NoError</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">mock</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">ExpectationsWereMet</span><span class="p">())</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Check <a href="https://github.com/pashagolub/pgxmock/blob/master/batch_test.go">pgxmock test cases</a> to know more!</p> <h2 id="what-about-prepare-and-deallocate">What about <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Prepare</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Deallocate</code>?</h2> <p>Since <strong>pgx</strong> doesn’t have a special struct to handle prepared statements, I simplified the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ExpectPrepare</code> struct in pgxmock. Instead of this</p> <div class="language-go highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>  <span class="n">mock</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">ExpectPrepare</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"articles_stmt"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">"SELECT (.+) FROM articles WHERE id = ?"</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span>
    <span class="n">ExpectQuery</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">.</span>
    <span class="n">WithArgs</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="m">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span>
    <span class="n">WillReturnRows</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">NewRows</span><span class="p">([]</span><span class="kt">string</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="s">"id"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">"title"</span><span class="p">})</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">AddRow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="m">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">"Betty B."</span><span class="p">))</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>one will just use this</p> <div class="language-go highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>  <span class="n">mock</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">ExpectPrepare</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"authors_stmt"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">"SELECT (.+) FROM authors WHERE id = ?"</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="n">mock</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">ExpectQuery</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"authors_stmt"</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span>
    <span class="n">WithArgs</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="m">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span>
    <span class="n">WillReturnRows</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">NewRows</span><span class="p">([]</span><span class="kt">string</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="s">"id"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">"title"</span><span class="p">})</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">AddRow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="m">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">"Betty B."</span><span class="p">))</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Pretty simple, huh?</p> <h2 id="ready-to-upgrade">Ready to Upgrade?</h2> <p>I motivate all users to upgrade to <strong>pgxmock v4</strong> to take advantage of these exciting enhancements and improvements. Whether you’re a long-time user or just starting with pgxmock, these changes will advance your PostgreSQL mocking experience.</p> <p>To get started with pgxmock v4, check your import statement:</p> <div class="language-go highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">import</span> <span class="s">"github.com/pashagolub/pgxmock/v4"</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>and/or run</p> <div class="language-sh highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>go get <span class="nt">-u</span> github.com/pashagolub/pgxmock/v4
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Thank you for your continued support and feedback. I look forward to seeing how <strong>pgxmock v4</strong> empowers your PostgreSQL database testing. If you have any questions or need assistance with the upgrade, please contact me on <a href="https://github.com/pashagolub/pgxmock">GitHub</a>.</p> <p>Happy mocking!</p> <p>Please, read and share! Glory to Ukraine! 💙💛</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="golang"/><category term="pgxmock"/><category term="what&apos;s new"/><category term="postgresql"/><category term="personal"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The new major release pgxmock v4 is out! This update adds long awaited support for `pgx.Batch` and completely rewrites the `Prepare` and `Deallocate` mocking implementation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Postgres.AI bot interview for PGSQL Phriday #015</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/postgresai-bot-interview-for-pgsql-phriday-015/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Postgres.AI bot interview for PGSQL Phriday #015"/><published>2024-02-02T19:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-02T19:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/postgresai-bot-interview-for-pgsql-phriday-015</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2024/postgresai-bot-interview-for-pgsql-phriday-015/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/postgres.ai-interview-1.jpeg"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-50932" src="/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/postgres.ai-interview-1.jpeg" alt="postgres.ai UUID interview" width="1024" height="1024"/></a>This month, we have an <a href="https://mydbanotebook.org/post/uuid-fight/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">invitation</a> from Lætitia to talk about UUIDs. UUIDs are a hot topic, and Cybertec wrote <a href="/en/tag/uuid/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">several posts</a> earlier. I have no particular story or use case to share, and then I remembered Nikolay Samokhvalov <a href="https://postgres.ai/blog/20240127-postges-ai-bot" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announced</a> the Postgres.AI bot to the public recently. I had early access to it, so I decided to talk about UUID with the artificial mind. I chose the form of an interview, forcing it to give short and structured answers whenever possible. So here we are! Meet the Postgres.AI one and only!</p> <h2>Hi postgres.ai! What is UUID and why everybody in database world obsessed with it?</h2> <p>UUID stands for Universally Unique Identifier. It is a 128-bit number used to uniquely identify information in computer systems. The database community is interested in UUIDs for several reasons:<br/> 1. <strong>Global Uniqueness</strong>: The probability of generating a duplicate UUID is very low, so it is highly suitable for distributed systems where coordination between nodes to generate unique values is unsuitable or impossible.<br/> 2. <strong>No Central Authority</strong>: UUIDs can be generated anywhere, by any system, without needing a central authority to manage the identifiers, which is beneficial for scalability and reduces single points of failure.<br/> 3. <strong>Standardized</strong>: UUIDs are standardized by the ITU-T Rec. X.667, ISO/IEC 9834-8:2005, and RFC 4122, so they're interoperable across different systems and technologies.<br/> 4. <strong>Variety of Algorithms</strong>: There are four standardized algorithms for generating UUIDs, identified by version numbers 1, 3, 4, and 5, each suitable for different use cases. For example, version 1 combines the MAC address and timestamp, version 4 is completely random, and versions 3 and 5 use namespace-based hashing.<br/> 5. <strong>Anonymity and Security</strong>: Some versions of UUIDs, like version 4, offer a high degree of anonymity, as they do not contain any information that can be linked back to the generator's identity.<br/> 6. <strong>Consistent Format</strong>: UUIDs have a standard structure and a string representation, which make them easy to store, transfer, and compare across systems.<br/> Within a database, using UUIDs as primary keys ensures each record is uniquely distinguishable from any other record, making replication and merging databases easier.<br/> For further technical details, you can refer to the documentation on UUID functions from the PostgreSQL manual: <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/uuid-ossp.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PostgreSQL Documentation - uuid-ossp</a>.<br/> Please note, before integrating UUIDs into a production system, it's essential to consider their implications on index performance and storage size, among other factors, and this must be carefully tested and evaluated.</p> <h2>Dear postgres.ai, what are the implications connected with integrating UUIDs in production systems?</h2> <p>Integrating UUIDs into production systems carries several implications that need to be carefully considered:<br/> 1. <strong>Performance Impact on Indexes</strong>: The random nature of UUIDs can lead to less efficient indexing as compared to sequential IDs. Since UUIDs are not ordered, each new UUID can be inserted at a random location within an index, potentially causing more page splits and leading to index fragmentation, which degrades write performance.<br/> 2. <strong>Increased Storage Requirements</strong>: UUIDs are 128-bit values (16 bytes) and therefore require more storage space than traditional 32-bit integers. This increased size affects not only the storage of the keys themselves but also the size of the indexes. More storage usage can increase costs and can impact cache hit rates.<br/> 3. <strong>Replication and Data Distribution</strong>: UUIDs are advantageous in replication scenarios since they can be created independently on different servers without risking collisions. This makes UUIDs suitable for distributed systems, where avoiding conflicts during data synchronization is essential.<br/> 4. <strong>Complexity for Developers</strong>: UUIDs are not as human-readable or as easy to debug as simple integer IDs, which can increase the complexity of development and troubleshooting processes.<br/> 5. <strong>Read Performance</strong>: Querying records via a UUID may be slower than using a sequential integer because UUIDs do not leverage any natural order, which can make range scans inefficient.<br/> 6. <strong>Compatibility and Integration</strong>: UUIDs are a standard data type supported across various platforms, which is beneficial when integrating multiple systems. However, it is important to ensure that all parts of the system (including ORM layers, database drivers, and other related tools) properly support UUIDs.<br/> 7. <strong>Data Migration</strong>: If existing systems are using integer-based identifiers, migrating to UUIDs can be challenging and will require careful planning to ensure that all references are correctly updated and that data integrity is maintained.<br/> It is crucial to assess the trade-offs of using UUIDs in the context of specific use cases. While they offer advantages in terms of global uniqueness and distribution, the potential impact on performance and storage should not be underestimated. To make an informed decision, conduct benchmark tests and consider UUID generation strategies that might mitigate some of the issues, like using UUIDs with a time-based or ordered component.<br/> A well-thought-out monitoring system is recommended to measure the impact of UUIDs on database performance. Tools like <code>pg_stat_statements</code>, <code>pg_stat_kcache</code>, and <code>auto_explain</code> are critical in this regard.<br/> The observations above are based on consolidated best practices and experiences discussed within the Postgres community, such as those reflected in <a href="https://github.com/postgres-ai/postgres-howtos/blob/main/0038_how_to_not_get_screwed_as_a_dba.md#4-performance" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Postgres How-Tos</a> by Nikolay Samokhvalov. Please remember that these scenarios must be tested before being applied to your production systems.</p> <h2>Please, provide me with a list of top-5 common use cases for UUID</h2> <p>The top-5 common use cases for using UUIDs in databases are:<br/> 1. <strong>Distributed Systems</strong>: UUIDs are perfect for distributed environments where data is created across multiple locations or nodes because they can be generated independently without the need for a centralized authority to ensure uniqueness.<br/> 2. <strong>Replication and Synchronization</strong>: In systems where data needs to be replicated or synchronized across different databases or services, UUIDs reduce the risk of key collisions and simplify the merge process.<br/> 3. <strong>Microservices Architecture</strong>: Each microservice can generate its own UUIDs for entities it manages, which is useful when combining data from different microservices without key conflicts.<br/> 4. <strong>Avoiding Information Disclosure</strong>: UUIDs prevent the easy discovery of the number of records or the creation order, adding security against information leakage compared to sequential IDs.<br/> 5. <strong>Object and Entity Identifier Outside of Databases</strong>: Because of their uniqueness, UUIDs can be used as identifiers for objects outside of the traditional database, such as in file systems or as part of web service APIs where a unique identifier is needed that cannot be easily guessed or incremented.</p> <h2>postgres.ai, what would you advise people looking into UUID usage?</h2> <p>When considering UUID usage, prioritize understanding your application's requirements for uniqueness, performance, and security. Assess the implications on data storage, index efficiency, and replication needs. Choose the appropriate UUID version, test extensively for your use case, and prepare for a larger storage footprint compared to traditional integer IDs. Always review and monitor performance after integrating UUIDs into production.</p> <h2>Thank you! You're a nice robot!</h2> <p>Thank you for the kind words! If you have any more questions about Postgres or need assistance with PostgreSQL-related challenges, feel free to ask. Remember, I'm here to help you with data performance, optimization, and best practices to keep your databases running smoothly. Keep exploring and happy database management!</p> <p>The post <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en/postgres-ai-bot-interview-for-pgsql-phriday-015/">Postgres.AI bot interview for PGSQL Phriday #015</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en">CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Pavlo Golub is interviewing postgres.ai chat bot about UUIDs for PGSQL Phriday 015 initiated by Lætitia Avrot The post Postgres.AI bot interview for PGSQL Phriday #015 appeared first on CYBERTEC PostgreSQL | Services &amp; Support.]]></summary></entry></feed>