<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/feed/by_tag/personal.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-04-07T14:18:03+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/feed/by_tag/personal.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A personal page with the blog and CV.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">hello world</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2015/formatting-and-links/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="hello world" /><published>2015-03-15T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2015-03-15T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2015/formatting-and-links</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2015/formatting-and-links/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my new blog! My name is <a href="https://postgresql.life/post/pavlo_golub/">Pavlo Golub</a>, and I have been working with PostgreSQL since 2002 when the version was 7.3. As a PostgreSQL developer and consultant, I am excited to share my insights and experiences with you through this personal blog that is not connected with my current or future employer.</p>

<p>PostgreSQL is an open-source relational database management system that is widely used in enterprise and web applications. It is known for its robustness, reliability, and scalability, making it an excellent choice for developers of all levels. Over the years, I have seen firsthand how PostgreSQL can transform data management and make applications more efficient.</p>

<p>This blog, which is hosted on Github Pages and built with Jekyll, will be dedicated to sharing my knowledge and experience with PostgreSQL. Whether you are a beginner looking for basic tutorials or an experienced developer seeking advanced techniques, this blog will cover a range of topics that will be useful to you. Additionally, I will share tips and tricks that I have learned throughout my career and discuss best practices for using PostgreSQL effectively.</p>

<p>My ultimate goal is to create a space where developers can come together to learn about PostgreSQL and how it can benefit their projects. I am thrilled to begin this journey with you and look forward to sharing my knowledge and insights with you.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to my new blog!]]></summary></entry></feed>