<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/feed/by_tag/personal.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-09-08T14:48:38+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/feed/by_tag/personal.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A personal page with the blog and CV.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Indexing `LIKE` Filters</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2023/indexing-like-filters/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indexing `LIKE` Filters" /><published>2023-09-08T13:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-08T13:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2023/indexing-like-filters</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2023/indexing-like-filters/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://postgresql.life/post/markus_winand/">Markus Winand</a> wrote a <a href="https://use-the-index-luke.com/sql/where-clause/searching-for-ranges/like-performance-tuning">great article</a> about why and how users should use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LIKE</code> operator in their workloads. It covers different approaches like Full-Text Search, Partial Index, Trigram Index, Materialized View, and query optimization. In summary, the talk primarily addresses challenges related to optimizing queries with leading wildcard LIKE searches and provides various strategies and techniques to overcome these challenges and improve database query performance.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="index" /><category term="FTS" /><category term="tips and tricks" /><category term="postgresql" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Markus Winand wrote a great article about why and how users should use LIKE operator in their workloads. It covers different approaches like Full-Text Search, Partial Index, Trigram Index, Materialized View, and query optimization. In summary, the talk primarily addresses challenges related to optimizing queries with leading wildcard LIKE searches and provides various strategies and techniques to overcome these challenges and improve database query performance.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">hello world</title><link href="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2015/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="hello world" /><published>2015-03-15T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2015-03-15T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2015/hello-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pashagolub.github.io/blog/2015/hello-world/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my new blog! My name is <a href="https://postgresql.life/post/pavlo_golub/">Pavlo Golub</a>, and I have been working with PostgreSQL since 2002 when the version was 7.3. As a PostgreSQL developer and consultant, I am excited to share my insights and experiences with you through this personal blog that is not connected with my current or future employer.</p>

<p>Thanks for checking out my blog, <strong>random pg scribbles</strong>. So, you might be wondering what that title means. The <strong>pg</strong> in the title stands for both <strong>PostgreSQL</strong>, the open-source database management system, and <strong>Pavlo Golub</strong> - that’s me! Basically, this blog is all about my exploration of the PostgreSQL database management system, which is often referred to as ‘Postgres’ for short. I use the term <strong>scribbles</strong> to convey the idea that the content here is somewhat informal and experimental. I’m not trying to write highly polished, fully-formed articles - instead, I’m sharing my thoughts and findings about Postgres in a more free-form, improvisational way.</p>

<p>As for the <strong>random</strong> part, that just means that the content of this blog isn’t necessarily organized around a specific theme or topic. I might write about different features of Postgres, share tips and tricks for using the software, or just muse on the broader database industry. The idea is that this blog is a space for me to explore my own interests and experiences with Postgres, and to share my thoughts with anyone else who might find them interesting. So if you’re into databases, or just enjoy reading the musings of a Postgres enthusiast, then stick around - there’s plenty of random postgres scribbles to come!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to my new blog!]]></summary></entry></feed>